Guide to the Oral Histories Documenting New Haven, Connecticut
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Interviews, Accession 2008-A-001
  - Dynia, Henry, 2005 March 9; computer file (WAV)
    Length (min): 22
    - Use copy, compact disc (Audio CD) (Box 42U)
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Edmonds, Rev. Dr. Edwin, 2004 February 16; computer file (WAV)
    The Reverend Doctor Edwin Edmonds arrived in New Haven in 1959 to serve as Pastor for the Dixwell United Church of Christ and quickly became involved in African American political activities. Edmonds came to New Haven from Greensboro, North Carolina, where he had been a Professor of Sociology at Bennett College and President of the local branch of the NAACP. He took on a number of racial issues through his church and through the NAACP. Edmonds recounts his efforts to integrate New Haven's schools and the discrimination he faced in the attempt to find affordable housing and his wife's difficulties finding a job as a teacher. He states that the local trade unions and the White Citizens' Council, a coalition of businessmen, both tried to restrict African American access to jobs and job training. Edmonds appealed to Mayor Richard Lee to put pressure on these groups. This led to the establishment training programs for African Americans who wanted to learn a trade and efforts by Lee to integrate the New Haven police force. Edmonds also cofounded the group Community Progress Incorporated, which was created to organize citizens into local advisory groups who could make recommendations for community development initiatives and to lobby cooperatively for civic improvements and fixes for neighborhood problems. Edmonds also talks about the creation of Head Start in New Haven.
    Interviewer: Hammond, Sarah
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Edmonds, Rev. Dr. Edwin, 2004 March 1; computer file (WAV)
    Length (min): 77
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Farr, Walter "Nick", 2006 March 21; computer file (WAV)
    Walter G. Farr graduated from Yale College in 1948 and from Yale Law School in 1951. In 1955, after working in New York City, he returned to New Haven and joined the Tyler Cooper law firm, where he worked as part of the outside counsel to the New Haven Redevelopment Agency. Farr also served as the head of the New Haven Civil Liberties Union and the Treasurer of the Human Relations Council. His work involved negotiating real estate deals for eminent domain and ensuring the legality of building condemnation. He describes himself as a liberal lawyer, committed to public interest. The interview focuses on his experiences with and perceptions of the New Haven Redevelopment Agency, its key supporters, and its activities. Farr talks about the goals of Redevelopment Administrator Edward J. Logue and Mayor Richard C. Lee and the civic ideals of Morris Tyler, James Cooper, Ralph Taylor, Harold Grabino. Referring to Robert Dahl's book Who Governs, Farr states that "who governed was us" namely, the community of liberal lawyers in New Haven. He says that the Redevelopment Agency and its lawyers were optimistic in their ability to improve New Haven. But he admits that in retrospect there were some mistakes in urban renewal projects that hurt New Haven's communities. He also discusses the culture of the New Haven Bar. In 1962, Farr began work for the US Agency for International Development (USAID). He later taught at New York University, directed the Model Cities Administration, and worked for the federal government.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Fernandez, Henry, 2007 February 14; computer file (WAV)
    Henry Fernandez moved to New Haven in 1990 to attend Yale Law School then co-founded LEAP (Leadership, Education and Athletics in Partnership) and served as its Executive Director for the next six years. As a college student in Boston, Fernandez had worked in summer programs for children who lived in public housing. He wanted to establish similar programs in New Haven. With fellow Yale student Matt Klein and Law Professor Anne Calabresi, Fernandez started LEAP. The interview focuses on LEAP's formative years. Fernandez discusses the assistance of local philanthropists like Roz and Jerry Meyer. He also talks about organizing the program and the relationships that he forged with the New Haven Housing Authority and Board of Education. LEAP was organized to serve low-income youth, primarily those living in public housing, and to provide them with educational and athletic activities in the summer. Fernandez envisioned this program as a way to deter violence in neighborhoods such as Church Street South, Elm Haven, Newhallville, and Dwight Kensington. He also intended LEAP to build relationships between the New Haven community and students at six local colleges, whom LEAP recruited as counselors. Fernandez talks fund raising, organizing programs, and ensuring the safety of counselors. He concludes by discussing the public image he helped craft for LEAP: an organization of diverse people from different backgrounds working together to improve community life for children.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Flanagan, John C., 2006 March 24; computer file (WAV)
    Interviewer: Errico, John
  - Fleming, Alba, 2006 May 4; computer file (WAV)
    As the daughter of a Jamaican woman and a Cherokee man, Alba Fleming identifies herself as West Indian rather than African American. An academically motivated student who eventually graduated from Yale University, Fleming was a senior at Hillhouse High School when the 1967 race riot erupted there. Fleming talks about the climate of the school in 1967 and 1968, describes the events that occurred on the day of the riot, and shares her experiences as a person of color during that time. Fleming explains that most of her friends were white and that she did not share the resentments that African American students faced. She did not feel disrespected by the white administration and did not participate in groups such as the Black Student Union. She discusses the tense atmosphere that developed in the wake of the riot and her fear that she would be targeted ay African American students for her associations with white students. The interview touches on the spread of the riot to the New Haven community and the subsequent attacks on businesses. Fleming also assesses the decline in Hillhouse High School's academic reputation in the decade after the riot.
    Interviewer: Johnson, Erin
    Length (min): 64
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Foote, George, 2005 April 14; computer file (WAV)
    George Foote taught history at Hillhouse High School from 1962 until 1970, when he became one of the first ten teachers at High School in the Community, an alternative school founded in 1970. Following a race riot at Hillhouse High School in 1967, Foote began to think about ways to defuse the racial tensions in New Haven's integrating public school system. He presented the idea for an alternative high school to fellow teachers and to the New Haven Board of Education, which he describes as a very progressive body in the late 1960s. Thanks to federal grants available for alternative schools through Title Three, Foote raised money to begin the school. Foote describes the teachers as mostly middle-class radicals and says that he was the only working-class teacher of the group. All, however, were committed to changing the educational system. High School in the Community attracted leaders of the Black Student Union at Hillhouse High School, including such students as Ronnie Barnes, its leader. Foote believed that the school could be a site to empower African Americans and the New Haven African American community and thus effect social change. The interview also covers his time at the Sound School, an alternative school devoted to teaching marine science, marine technology, and sailing. Foote talks about alternative and magnet schools and issues of race and social class, focusing on special challenges for middle-class African American students and parents.
    Interviewer: Anderson, Christa
    Length (min): 59
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Franceschi, Norma, 2004 November 12
    Length (min): 43
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Fusco, Edmund, 2007 February 28; computer file (WAV)
    Edmund Fusco was a real estate developer who became involved in the Church Street mall project in the early 1960s. Mayor Dick Lee and redevelopment leader Edward Logue initially approached a New York developer named Roger Stevens. Stevens worked on the project for a few years, before selling his interest to Fusco. Fusco discusses the reason for the failure of the project, concluding that a shopping center in an urban area made very little sense in an era of suburbanization and sprawl. Suburbanites, he says, had no interest in coming downtown to shop, and Fusco regrets that he didn't see this at the time. In addition, Fusco discusses the possibilities of a public/private partnership. Can both the city and the developer benefit from a redevelopment project? Must one win out to the disadvantage of the other? Fusco concludes that, in theory, such a partnership can work, but individual personalities make it difficult in practice.
    Interviewer: Lewis, Dain
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Genece, Gerde, 2007 February 23; computer file (WAV)
    Gerde Genece, a Haitian American, lived with her children in the Hill neighborhood of New Haven until 1995 but moved to Fair Haven because of the drug-related crime. Genece and her neighbors organized a neighborhood watch in her new community to fight intimidation and prevent violence. She discusses the time her son was mugged and kidnapped and how it motivated her to stand up to criminals in her neighborhood. Genece explains that her neighbors have all started to watch out for one another and have become involved with the local police station in order to improve their neighborhoods. She also talks about her life as a person of color in New Haven and the prejudices she has experienced.
    Interviewer: Jaimez, Norma
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Gillette, Jack, 2003 June 12; computer file (WAV)
    After graduating from Harvard and the Urban Teaching Program at Wesleyan, Jack Gillette took a job teaching history and social studies at Hillhouse High School in New Haven. Gillette discusses his reasons for choosing to work at an underprivileged, almost completely African American, high school, and the challenges he faced in so doing. Gillette arrived in New Haven in 1970, just as the teachers went on strike for the first time. He discusses his decision to join the strike, and reflects on the relationship of the teachers' union to the larger labor movement. He also discusses the obligations of the teacher to his students, and how this affects unionism and labor activism among teachers. After the 1970 strike, the teachers walked out again in 1973, and once more in 1975, before striking a binding bargaining agreement. Gillette left teaching in 1980, but maintains connections with the profession and the teachers' union through his wife, who continued to teach.
    Length (min): 78
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Gilvarg, Karyn, 2004 December 5; computer file (WAV)
    Karyn Gilvarg arrived in New Haven to attend architecture school in 1975, and is now the Executive Director of City Planning for the city of New Haven. In its early years, she recalls, the City Planning department was basically a "handmaiden" for the Redevelopment Agency, focusing on economic development and urban renewal, rather than city planning as such. Although Gilvarg missed the peak years of redevelopment and urban renewal under the administration of Richard Lee, she reports that redevelopment schemes and extensive plans for downtown New Haven continued well into the 1970s and 1980s. The downtown mall, in particular, dominated the attention of New Haven city planners for much of this period. Gilvarg also discusses the future of New Haven city planning, explaining that providing incentives for biotech companies to move to New Haven and increasing the availability of housing downtown are two directions in which she hopes to move.
    Interviewer: Garcia, Tomas
    Length (min): 50
    - Use copy, compact disc (Audio CD) (Box 54U)
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Gorang, James, 2003 November 25; computer file (WAV)
    James Gorang is a teacher at the Dwight Elementary School in downtown New Haven. Gorang arrived at Dwight in 1987, and spent fifteen years as a Special Education teacher before moving into Special Ed administration. Gorang talks about the make-up, curriculum, and pedagogy at Dwight School, which recently converted to a focus on civics and social sciences. Gorang discusses his relationship with his students and their parents, and the relative importance of parental involvement in elementary education. In addition, he speaks to the challenges of teaching towards standardized tests, as required by the recent No Child Left Behind legislation. Gorang talks about the appeal of the Dwight Elementary School, as compared to other New Haven elementary schools, and the opportunitites that the school's location -- near Yale and the cultural offerings of downtown New Haven -- provides for its teachers and students.
    Interviewer: Chen, Joe
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Gordon, Angus, 2006 November 13; computer file (WAV)
  - Grady, Charles, 2005 March 17; computer file (WAV)
    Charles Grady joined the New Haven police department in 1959, and remained on the force for 32 years. In the late 1960s, he was assigned to the Youth Services Division of the NHPD. Among other activities, Grady worked as a plainclothes detective within New Haven high schools. Grady describes a number of incidents that occurred during his years in the schools, including a threatened take over of Lee High School by a black nationalist organization, which may or may not have been the Black Panthers. Grady commends Mayor Richard Lee for his handling of the 1967 riots, suggesting that the Mayor's willingness to talk with members of the black community, including the Hill Parents' Association, prevented the city from burning. He also suggests that the administration of Yale University played an important role in facilitating discussion and keeping the peace in the city during the late 1960s.
    Length (min): 24
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Grant, Edward, 2005 December 6; computer file (WAV)
    Edward Grant was born in New Haven in 1922. During World War II, Grant was stationed in New Orleans, deep in the segregated South. Grant was involved in a few minor acts of civil disobedience in New Orleans, and returned from the war with a determination to overturn racism and segregation in New Haven. Grant pursued this goal on a number of fronts -- working to include black history in school curriculums, involving himself the Civil Rights group CORE (Congress of Racial Equality), and working closely with the Q-House community center in New Haven. Grant discusses his involvement with Democratic party politics in New Haven, including his work to secure the election of Mayor Richard Lee. In retrospect, Grant recognizes the shortcomings of Lee's redevelopment plans, but insists that the blame should be placed on the state of Connecticut, not on Lee. Grant talks about the strained relationship between Yale University and New Haven's African-American community, and discusses his relationships with Yale Presidents Bartlett Giamatti and Kingman Brewster. Grant also describes the 1967 Black Panther Trials and the protests and riots that surrounded them.
    Interviewer: Raymond, Sarah
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Greenberg, Alan, 2006 April 3; computer file (WAV)
  - Hamenachem, Rachel, 2007 February 27; computer file (WAV)
    Rachel Hamenachem runs the Westville Kosher Market. Born in Jerusalem, Hamenachem moved to New Haven in 1985. Her husband opened the Market with a partner, whose retirement forced Rachel Hamenachem into the business. The market caters to a small but faithful clientele, how appreciate the freshness of the market's meat, its ability to meet special orders and special requests, and the personalized service provided by Hamenachem. Hamenachem considers her store to be part of the community in which it's located, and takes pride in knowing the names and stories of her customers. After 20 years in the business, however, Hamenachem fears that small speciality stores may be on their last legs in New Haven. As grocery stores pick up more kosher products, the Westville Kosher Market finds its client base shrinking. In years past, Hamenachem recalls, there were multiple kosher delis, butchers, and bakeries on Whalley Avenue between downtown New Haven and Westville. At the time of the interview, Hamenachem's market is the only kosher speciality shop left.
    Interviewer: Fitts, Alexis
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Hirshman, Rhea, 2007 March 2; computer file (WAV)
    Rhea Hirschman was a leading participant in the women's movement in New Haven in the 1970s and early 1980s. She discusses her initiation into the women's movement through a group called Women vs. Connecticut, which aimed to challenge the state's anti-aborition legislation before Roe vs. Wade. After Roe, Hirschman continued her participation in a variety of women's causes. She worked closely with the Speaker's Bureau, which sent individuals or teams of women to various public sites to lecture on causes related to women's rights, sexuality, or health. Hirschman was involved with the New Haven Women's Center, one of longest operating centers of its kind, and took part in grass roots community education efforts as well as working with domestic violence and rape crisis centers. She also had a radio show and ran a women's book shop for six years. Hirschman also discusses the importance of cultural prodcutions to the dissemination of feminist ideas, mentioning specifically the Theater of Light and Shadow, a political theater group, and the influence of feminist folk, rock, and pop music.
    Interviewer: Tallevi, Ashley
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Hladkyj, Irene, 2006 March 4; computer file (WAV)
    Irene Hladkyj moved to New Haven in 1950, joining an already sizable and active Ukrainian community. Hladkyj describes the church as the centerpiece of the Ukrainian community, and remembers that she "always, always" lived near other Ukrainians. The peak years of Ukrainian immigration to the U.S., Hladkyj reports, were between 1947 and 1953. After this point, immigration slackened and the Ukrainian population of New Haven began to decline. Hladkyj raised children, and worked in an number of factories in the area, including the A.C. Gilbert toy factory. Hladkyj describes the founding of a Ukrainian Heritage Center in New Haven in 1984. The center was designed to preserve Ukrainian culture and to show Americans "what it's all about." Hladkyj considers the preservation of Ukrainian heritage a personal mission, and describes a number of benefits over the years designed to raise money for assorted Ukrainian causes, including a concert to benefit the children of Chernobyl.
    Interviewer: Sawka, Ilyana
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Jacobs, Stanley, 2006 March 29; computer file (WAV)
  - Johnson, Mary, 2003 June 17; computer file (WAV)
    Mary Johnson attended New Haven Teacher's College during the Great Depression. After graduation, she taught in Milford, CT, then in Cheshire, CT, eventually moving to Troupe Middle School in New Haven. Johnson's husband worked at Winchester Repeating Arms factory, where he was very involved in the union, before being hired by his international as an organizer. Early in her tenure at Troupe, Johnson became involved with the New Haven Federation of Teachers, and was a lead negotiator in teachers' strikes in 1968, 1970, 1973, and 1975. Johnson spent several nights in jail during these strikes. Johnson is proud of her union activities, and recognizes the real gains achieved by the striking teachers. She suggests, however, that the radicalism which underlay the 1970s strikes has dissipated, leaving a class of teachers disinterested in their union and unaware of its past.
    Length (min): 80, 29
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Joyner, Dr. Edward, 2005 March 17; computer file (WAV)
    Dr. Edward Joyner arrived in New Haven in 1968 and began teaching sociology and African-American history at Hillhouse high School in 1970. Joyner aligns himself with a crop of activist teachers who arrived in New Haven in the late 60s and early 70s. He talks about the student movement which sought to bring courses in African American history and literature into the Hillhouse curriculum and to hire teachers and counselors more in touch with the African-American experience in New Haven. He describes a great deal of generational tension among teachers at Hillhouse, between those older conservative teachers who opposed change, and younger leftists who supported the student movement. Joyner views the New Haven student movement as a rational, organized, grassroots attempt to create real change in the school system. He also talks about the founding of High School in the Community, and its effect on Hillhouse High School.
    Length (min): 39
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Keegan, Laura, 2007 February 23; computer file (WAV)
    Laura Keegan recently moved from State College, PA to the Chatham Square Area of North Haven. She shares an apartment with her boyfriend, Walter, who works at Sikorski. Keegan talks about her adopted neighborhood, talking at length about her landlord, Arthur. Upon moving into the neighborhood, Keegan had no expectations, but quickly heard a number of negative stories about Fair Haven from her co-workers. These stories, she says, have proven entirely untrue, and she comments on Fair Haven's bad reputation, suggesting that it's wholly undeserved. She is mostly happy with her neighbors, but has a few suggestions for increasing feelings of community in the Chatham Square area, including the use of internet forums. Keegan compares New Haven to State College, concluding that both are typical college towns. Keegan discusses her artistic ambitions, and her plans to apply to graduate school.
    Interviewer: Lieber, Sarah
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Kinzly, Mark, 2005 April 8; computer file (WAV)
    Born and raised in New York City, Mark Kinzly is the child of drug addicted parents, and a former alcoholic and drug abuser himself. He came to New Haven in 1984, and spent the next five or six years attempting to get clean. He describes the drug scene in New Haven, and explains why crack cocaine proved so devastating to the African American community. Kinzly discusses the correlation between illness (particularly Hepatitis and HIV) and intravenous drug use, and describes the birth of the needle exchange program in New Haven in 1990. Starting as a grassroots effort, a number of health workers and addiction advocates began the program to offer addicts clean needles in order to curb the spread of infections. In 1991, Kinzly hit rock bottom and managed to get clean. After doing so, he began to volunteer at the New Haven needle exchange program. Kinzly describes his experiences working in the needle exchange van, and lists some of the reasons for the success of the New Haven program, as well as the challenges faced by needle exchange nationwide.
    Interviewer: Lu, Tiffany
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Kramer, Sara, 2004 February 27; computer file (WAV)
    Interviewer: Farber, Hannah
    Length (min): 49
  - Krick, John, 2006 March 31; computer file (WAV)
  - Kubler, Elizabeth, 2004 February 18; computer file (WAV)